<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Fvll and faithfvll accompt of the passages betwixt the parish of Michaels Cornehill (met in a vestry) the ministers and elders of the fourth classis of the province of London, and Mr. J. Symonds, late of Roterdam in Holland touching his admission to the expository lecture in that parish in the room of Mr. Burroughs deceased : published, in the name, and by the unanimous consent of the classes met at the vestry of Mary-ax-Hill, Febr. 1. 1646 as a remedy against the manifold misreports and censures to confidently delivered by some, and too credulously received by others, concerning the beginning, proceeding and conclusion of that motion : at a meeting of the fourth classis, Feb. 1. 1646 : resolved upon the question, nemine contradicente, that this vindication of the vestry of Michaels Cornhill, and the fourth classis of the province of London, concerning the motion of Mr. Symonds to bee lecturer in that parish, bee presented to some of the licencers for the presse, and forthwith printed / subscribed by order of the fourth classis, by W. Wickins ...</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 51 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A40543</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12922251</idno>
  <idno type="VID">95407</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2264186779</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing F2281</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R7983</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">12922251</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A40543)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 95407)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 982:25)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Fvll and faithfvll accompt of the passages betwixt the parish of Michaels Cornehill (met in a vestry) the ministers and elders of the fourth classis of the province of London, and Mr. J. Symonds, late of Roterdam in Holland touching his admission to the expository lecture in that parish in the room of Mr. Burroughs deceased : published, in the name, and by the unanimous consent of the classes met at the vestry of Mary-ax-Hill, Febr. 1. 1646 as a remedy against the manifold misreports and censures to confidently delivered by some, and too credulously received by others, concerning the beginning, proceeding and conclusion of that motion : at a meeting of the fourth classis, Feb. 1. 1646 : resolved upon the question, nemine contradicente, that this vindication of the vestry of Michaels Cornhill, and the fourth classis of the province of London, concerning the motion of Mr. Symonds to bee lecturer in that parish, bee presented to some of the licencers for the presse, and forthwith printed / subscribed by order of the fourth classis, by W. Wickins ...</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 18 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Rich. Cotes,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1646.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Symonds, J.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Church polity.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-02 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-02 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:95407:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:95407:1"/>
            <p>A FVLL and FAITHFVLL <hi>ACCOMPT</hi> Of the Passages betwixt <hi>the Parish of Michaels Cornehill</hi> (met in a Vestry) <hi>the Ministers and Elders of the fourth Classis</hi> of the Province of London, <hi>and Mr. J. Symonds,</hi> late of <hi>Roterdam</hi> in <hi>Holland;</hi> touching his admission to the Expository Lecture in that Parish in the room of Mr. <hi>Burroughs</hi> deceased.</p>
            <p>PUBLISHED, <hi>In the name, and by the unanimous consent of the</hi> Classis met at the Vestry of <hi>Mary</hi>-at-<hi>Hill, Febr.</hi> 1. 1646. as a remedy against the manifold misreports and censures too confidently delivered by some, and too credulously received by others, concerning the beginning, proceeding and conclusion of that motion.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>By honour and dishonour, by evill report and g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>od report, as deceivers and yet true,</hi>
               <bibl>2 Cor. 6. 8.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Apud Christianos non qui patitur, sed qui facit contumel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>am miser est. <bibl>Hieron. Marco Presbytero Celedonsi. <hi>Tom.</hi> 2. p. 315.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="order_to_print">
                        <head>At a meeting of the fourth Classis, <hi>Feb. 1. 1646.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Resolved upon the Question, Nemine contradicente,</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>That this Vindication of the Vestry of <hi>Michaels Cornhill,</hi> and the fourth Classis of the Province of <hi>London,</hi> concerning the motion of Mr. <hi>Symonds</hi> to bee Lecturer in that Parish, bee presented to some of the Licencers for the Presse, and forthwith printed. <hi>Subscribed by order of the fourth Classis, By</hi> W. Wickins <hi>Scribe to the said Clas<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                                 <desc>••</desc>
                              </gap>.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="imprimatur">
                        <p>Imprimatur</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Ja. Cranford.</signed>
                           <date>Feb. 4. 1646.</date>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London</hi> Printed by <hi>Rich. Cotes,</hi> 1646.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:95407:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:95407:2"/>
            <head>A Full and Faithfull Accompt of the passages betwixt the Parish of <hi>Michael Cornhill,</hi> (met in a Vestry) the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters and Elders of the fourth <hi>Classis</hi> of the Province of <hi>London,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Symonds</hi> late of <hi>Roterdam</hi> in <hi>Holland,</hi> touching his admission to the expository Lecture in that Parish in the roome of Mr. <hi>Burroughs</hi> deceased. PUBLISHED, As a remedy against the manifold misreports too confidently delivered by some, and too credu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lously received by others, concerning the beginning, proceeding, and conclusion of that motion.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F the misrepresentations of this matter (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in men of various interests and affections are engaged) had stayd within the compasse of some <hi>slight and inconsiderable differences, or had beene confined to a few, or to men of too meane qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie to produce both a personall and reall prejudice against the Reformation in hand,</hi> wee should have thought it a point of the <hi>prudence of the Serpent,</hi> prescribed by our Saviour, <hi>Matth.</hi> 10. 16. to betake our selves to none other defence of the <hi>innocency of the Dove</hi> then patience and si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, with hope that it would not bee more for our reproach then for our reputation, according to the saying of <hi>Solomon, Prov.</hi> 19. 11. in such a case to passe by an offence, without taking notice of it so farre as to put our selves to the service of a publique Apology.</p>
            <p>But since <hi>in all these respects</hi> of importance forementioned we have found it contrary (in matter of fact) and have cause to forecast as much evill of the effect to follow, (if some especiall Antidote bee not tempered and timely administred to prevent the offensive and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:95407:3"/> injurious operations whereto they tend, and since there want not those who have thought us as much too remisse, as others have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported us too rigid in our dealing with Mr. <hi>Symonds,</hi> wee conceive it a part of that duty which we owe To the truth of the cause; To our owne integritie in the carriage of it; To the honour of the Government wherewith wee are intrusted, and To the desires of divers of our Venerable Brethren, (frequently and affectionately ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed to some of us) to take off the imputations (cast upon the whole businesse and upon the <hi>Vestry,</hi> and <hi>Classis</hi> with reference unto it,) by a calme and conscientious relation by what meanes it was presented to us, what entertainment it had among us, and how it was at last dismissed by us; which was in this manner.</p>
            <p>When the Ministers and other members of the fourth <hi>Classis</hi> of the Province of <hi>London</hi> were come together, to consult of such things<note place="margin">On Munday Decemb. 7.</note> as appertained to their association, one of the Elders produced a paper sent to the <hi>Classis</hi> from the Vestry of <hi>Michaels Cornehill,</hi> who met the third of <hi>December,</hi> 1646. and at that meeting agreed and ordered <hi>That Deputy Mosse, Collonel Bellamy,</hi> and Mr. <hi>James Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin should represent unto the Classis</hi> (of which that Parish is a part) <hi>the desire of the subscribers to the exposition Lectures, for the setting Mr. Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds in the place of Mr. Burroughs deceased, and to report back to the Parish at a Vestry (called for that purpose) the result of the said Classis con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the same businesse. And that all such as can informe any thing that may concerne the same may have libertie to appeare before the said Classis to speake what they know therein.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which paper after it was read, a reverend Minister of his ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintaince<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>H. R.</hi>
               </note> made answer,</p>
            <p>First, by commendation of Mr. <hi>Symonds</hi> for his Ministeriall gifts, and good disposition; And</p>
            <p>Secondly, by way of exception against him, for holding a loose opinion touching liberty of conscience, and <hi>toleration of different religions,</hi> contrary to the solemne Vow and Covenant of the three Kingdomes; which taken into debate as in order to an answer of advice for the case in question, and not otherwise, the unanimous consent of the Classis was set downe in two particulars.</p>
            <p>First, <hi>That the finall determination of any thing concerning</hi> Mr. <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds bee deferred untill the Classis may bee satisfied that hee is orthodox in judgement.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>That untill a setled Lecturer bee chosen, and approved of by the Classis, the names of those that supply the said Lecture bee given in
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:95407:3"/> to the Presbytery of the said Parish five dayes before, that they may approve of him or them.</hi> At the first a dayes warning was propounded, but it was moved by a another reverend Divine well affected to Mr. <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>I. C.</hi>
               </note> and to that Lecture likewise, that it might bee five dayes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that if any named to the Elders were upon just cause denied by them, there might bee competent time to procure a supply by some other.</p>
            <p>And this as it was desired in favour both to the Lecture and Lectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer Mr. <hi>Symonds,</hi> so was it out of good will to both, and to him that made the motion, readily resolved on by the <hi>Classis,</hi> and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently drawne up into an order by the Scribe. The word <hi>Order</hi> (by the way) doth import no more power then a Vote (which is the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sult of their minds who are the major part of the meeting) but one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly more union when the resolution is made with a <hi>nemine contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cente;</hi> and that this and no more was the mind of the <hi>Classis, that is, to answer a request for advice by giving advice as the case required,</hi> was expressely and with joynt consent professed by all the Brethren in<note place="margin">1646. Decemb. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> the next Classicall meeting, <hi>December</hi> the 22. 1646. which should the rather be taken for an advice, then a rule or binding order, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause the motion was presented not from a Parochiall or Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gationall Presbytery, but from a Vestry, which stands in no such direct subordination to a <hi>Classis</hi> as the Parochiall Presbytery doth. And could they doe lesse in dutie to God, in conscience to the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, in religious prudence, and Christian charitie to their Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren? They did, and doe conceive they might have done more by vertue of the Ordinance of Parliament for ordination of Ministers <hi>Aug.</hi> 28. 1646. which, in the comprehensive sense of it, they take to extend unto Lecturers, that they are to come under the same course of admission and approbation with other Ministers remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving from one place to another.</p>
            <p>This interpretation they were taught to make of the Ordinance by the practise of the Honorable Committee for plundred Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters, and confirmed in it by the judgement and proceeding of their Reverend Brethren in a neighbour Classis.</p>
            <p>First, for the Committee, though the Order by which they sit, bearing date <hi>July</hi> 27. 1643. expresly mention their nomination of Ministers to a Parsonage or Benefice, naming none other, yet they take the same course with Lecturers that come to their cognizance, that is, they send them for approbation to the Assembly of Divines; so was Mr. <hi>Simpson</hi> (Mr. <hi>Symonds</hi> his especiall friend) sent with an
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:95407:4"/> Order to the Assembly for a Lecture at <hi>Dulwich</hi> in <hi>Surrey,</hi> and since again (and that very lately) there was the like reference of him to the Assembly for his setting up a Lecture in <hi>Summerset-house</hi> in the <hi>Strand;</hi> and this week the like Order was sent from the same Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee to the Assembly, for examination and approbation of a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Orthodox and well approved Presbyterian, Mr. <hi>F. R.</hi> for his admission to a Lecture in <hi>East-Greenwich.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, for the judgement and practise of the neighbour Clas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sis, that is legible in a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>etter written from Mr. <hi>J. C.</hi> to Mr. <hi>Sp.</hi> in these words,</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>Sir, <hi>You having been chosen Lecturer by the Company of Mercers in the Parish of</hi> Bartholomew <hi>the</hi> Exchange; <hi>I am desired by our Classis at our meeting,</hi> December 2. 1646. <hi>to signifie to you, that it is ordered, That you forbeare execution of any Ministeriall function there, untill you have submitted your self to the examination of our Classicall Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, according to the Ordinance of Parliament in such cases provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</hi> Sir, I rest</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Yours <hi>J. C.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>And for the proceedings of them both, there is very good rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son; for if Lecturers should be exempt from the rules prescribed in the Ordinance, there might bee so many of them set up to cry down what is established (according to the Word of God, and by authority of Parliament,) both in Doctrine and in government, as would amount to the most dangerous kinde of toleration that could bee.</p>
            <p>The administration of the Sacraments (the other chief part of the Ministers commission) nor any act else which Lecturers leave to incumbent Pastors to perform, are of such either use or force for good or evill as preaching is, thereafter as it is managed by men, whether of sound or unsound apprehensions in matters of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</p>
            <p>Nor did the <hi>Classis</hi> overdoe their duty, in giving cautionary ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice concerning such as should bee set up to preach in <hi>Mr. Symonds</hi> his stead, since a substitute (if hee bee not Orthodox) may mislead the people, and disturb their peace, as well as he whose place he sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyeth; and it hath been observed in this City, that for some Lectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, <note n="*" place="margin">Mr. <hi>Symps.</hi> the Antinom. for Mr. <hi>Cr.</hi>
               </note> such have been taken to preach in their absence, as have been articled against for erroneous and dangerous opinions, and for them, and for miscarriages answerable to them, upon conviction have been censured by publique Authority.</p>
            <p>And on this Lecture both the Vestry of <hi>Michaels Cornhill</hi> and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:95407:4"/> the Classis had reason to looke with a more observant eye for two causes especially.</p>
            <p>1. Because the most of those, who have the chiefe hand in the choice of the men, and procurement of the maintenance for that and such like Lectures, shew no minde to admit of any Presbyterian, how godly and well gifted soever, to read or preach them as in an ordinary course.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Because these Lectures are not (as many others) <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rochial,</hi> set up for the benefit, or maintained at the charge of a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Parish or Parishioner, but rather <hi>provinciall,</hi> both for the people of all Parishes in the City to be present at them, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributers to them.</p>
            <p>Yet was this act of the Classis so offensively taken by some, that they spake against it as a Presbyteriall presumption, and severity, of a farre higher and harsher straine then prelaticall usurpation: one saying, <hi>the Order was as high as Pauls steeple;</hi> another, <hi>that it was ten times more rigid then the practice of the prelates, who never put any to five dayes premonition for taking of a turne in any Lecture;</hi> and some talked of complaining to the Parliament, as if it were a presage, the Presbyterians taking so much upon them in their first Classicall As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembly, would bee like (in time to come, if they were not curbed by the supreme power of the kingdome) to transcend the prelaticall tyranny, as much as <hi>Rehoboam</hi> threatned to exceed the severity of <hi>Solomon,</hi> when hee said, <hi>My little finger shall bee thicker then my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers loines, 1 King.</hi> 12. 10. when all was no more then might have beene done by a particular Minister, or private Christian, if hee had beene consulted with as the Classis was.</p>
            <p>For which of them may not give an advice to them that aske it? Do not they who for this take offence at the Classis, take much more upon them, when without any authority at all (for ought yet ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth) they gather Churches out of Churches, admit of Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers with a speciall Covenant, set up these expository Lecturers, make choyce of the men, and change the times and places of their preaching at their pleasure? And for this last particular, if all that are able and willing to bee at cost with a Lecturer of their owne electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, should use the like liberty, there would bee many a dangerous stumbling blocke layed in the way of the weake; who, not able to judge of diversity of Doctrines, might take meere blasphemy for Orthodox Divinity, as the <hi>Antitrinitarians, Antiscripturists, Enthusi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>asts</hi> and other Hereticks doe; and might perhaps become such pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficients▪
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:95407:5"/> from bad to worse, as to bee brought at last to thinke it a service to God to kill his servants, as our Saviour foretold of some in the 16 of <hi>John v.</hi> 2. by which expression, wee desire not to put any suspition of sinfull complyance with such desperate Dogma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tists upon our dissenting brethren, (who we doubt not abhorre such impieties as wee doe,) but to note the ill consequence which is like to fall out, if in these times, so luxurient in pernicious opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Lecturers should be left out of the rule of the Ordinance, and come under no tryall of their qualifications or Tenets, but as <hi>sui juris,</hi> should bee allowed to set up office, and exercise, when and where they thinke meet, without accompt to any, or consent of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny but themselves, and those who subscribe to their salarie.</p>
            <p>Among whom, though some out of an equall excesse of love to <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependency,</hi> &amp; of dislike to the <hi>Presbytery,</hi> take more liberty to traduce and censure the <hi>Vestry</hi> and <hi>Classis</hi> as associated together, then Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stianity would allow of, though but against one Minister or Elder taken singly by himselfe, yet would not the <hi>Classis</hi> thereby be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked out of their soft pace of patience and moderation towards Master <hi>Symonds,</hi> and therefore hearing hee was come to <hi>London</hi> to carry on the Lecture, (as Master <hi>Burroughes</hi> had done) at their next meeting, which was <hi>Jan:</hi> 4. 1646. they appointed Master <hi>Ley</hi> with two more of their Members Colonell <hi>Hooker,</hi> and Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell <hi>Bellamy</hi> to acquaint Master <hi>Symonds</hi> with the Ordinance of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, for ordination of Ministers, with reference to his choyce to be expository Lecturer in Master <hi>Burroughes</hi> his place at <hi>Michaels Cornhill.</hi> Whereupon on Wednesday <hi>Jan:</hi> 6. Master <hi>Symonds</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to visit Master <hi>Bellamy</hi> at his owne house, hee told him the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foresaid resolution of the <hi>Classis,</hi> and desired him to nominate a time and place for that purpose, that they which were appointed by the <hi>Classis</hi> might come unto him; but with respect to Master <hi>Ley,</hi> Master <hi>Symonds</hi> desired him to appoint the time and place, and hee would give them the meeting there. And on Thursday Jan: 7. they made choyce of Friday <hi>Jan:</hi> 8. at 3 of the Clocke in the after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noone at Master <hi>Leyes</hi> house, and sent present word thereof to Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster <hi>Symonds,</hi> but hee made answer by the Messenger of the <hi>Classis, That hee could not possibly come at that time, because hee was in an unsettled condition, and hee had other occasions which hee was to goe about at that time, but hee had declared his minde in full to Master</hi> Bellamy, <hi>so that be could certifie them as much as if bee were there himselfe; but when hee was a little settled be would come to Master</hi> Leys <hi>house, and satisfie him in any thing that he did desire.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:95407:5"/>
            <p>This Message was brought to Master <hi>Ley</hi> who presently sent him backe that brought it with a request to Master <hi>Symonds,</hi> that himselfe would prescribe both time and place, since that choyce made with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out him was so inconvenient for his occasions. To that hee made returne <hi>that hee was sorry Master</hi> Ley <hi>should trouble himselfe so much to send to him so often, but truly hee could not possibly appoint either an houre or day when they should come to him, or hee to them, in regard of the unsettled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of his condition, because hee was but lately come over and had no habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of his owne, and his bookes and other things lay some in one place and some in another, and hee was going about to looke for a place to settle himselfe in; and till then hee entreated them to forbeare him; Besides this hee said (as before) hee had made his minde knowne so fully to Master</hi> Bellamy, <hi>that hee could satisfie Master</hi> Ley <hi>as much as if hee spake with him himselfe: neverthelesse so soone as hee was in any settled condition, hee would repaire to Master</hi> Leys <hi>lodging, and satisfie him in any thing that hee should de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Where that hee saith of <hi>Master</hi> Leys <hi>troubling himselfe so much,</hi> was but his curtesie to him, that hee might trouble him the lesse, and his duty to the <hi>Classis,</hi> having undertaken the service upon their appointment, and being to give an accompt thereof at the next Clas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sicall meeting.</p>
            <p>Notwithstanding this Master <hi>Symonds</hi> came on Friday foremen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned to Master <hi>Leys</hi> house, and of the two Colonels, one came with him, the other met him there, but Master <hi>Ley</hi> having no inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation at all of the change of his minde, and having businesse at <hi>Westminster</hi> which detained him till night, (which yet hee would have dispensed with if hee had knowne Master <hi>Symonds</hi> like the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter son in the parable, <hi>Mat:</hi> 21. 28, 29. would have beene better then his word) came not home untill they were gone, though they staid somewhat long.</p>
            <p>This absence of Master <hi>Ley</hi> (from the place and time of his owne and his Colleagues choyce) was so farre mistaken and misreported by some, as if hee had carelesly failed, or purposely falsified his word with those hee should have met; and by Master <hi>Symonds</hi> his speech to the subscribers at Master <hi>Shutes</hi> house, it was so conceived by the hearers, because hee concealed his former refusall to give meeting that day, and the change of his minde, which was altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther unknowne to Master <hi>Ley,</hi> untill at his returne hee was told they had beene at his house, but before hee came had departed thence.</p>
            <p>The next day being <hi>lan.</hi> 9. Mr. <hi>Symonds</hi> wrote this ensuing Letter to Mr. <hi>Bellamy.</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:95407:6"/>
                  <head>For Colonell <hi>Bellamy</hi> his good friend.</head>
                  <p>Sir, understanding that such a report of mee came to your parish, lest it might worke a disaffection against me, I held it fit to intreat you to doe mee the fav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ur to relate to them what I said to you, and to present my respects to them, and my desire and hope that they will bee pleased to grant me their consent to preach in their Church, as formerly they did to Mr. Burroughts I held it meet to give them this due respect, and so I rest,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Yours in Christ to serve you, J. Symonds.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>The Letter is short, too short to be wel understood without some sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, which is thus to be made out. <hi>Sir, understanding such a report of me,</hi> that is, of holding for <hi>toleration of diversitie of religions, came to your Parish.</hi> It was five dayes before related in the <hi>Classis,</hi> and upon that ground the advice was given to the Parish of <hi>Michaels Cornhill</hi> at the same time, but Mr. <hi>Symonds</hi> by this would take no notice of that: <hi>I intreat you to doe mee the favour to relate to them what I said to you;</hi> which was for substance the same that he afterward returned to the three messengers together, and that's delivered in the ensuing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation Hee was unwilling it seemes to commit to writing ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the report or his Apology, for reasons best knowne unto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe. And for his <hi>desire and hope that they would grant him their consent,</hi> thereto the answer returned (the next day after the date of this Letter) was as followeth.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>At a Vestry held the tenth of <hi>January 1646.</hi> in the Church of <hi>Michaels Cornehill London.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Forasmuch as the businesse concerning Mr. Symonds being Lecturer here is depending before the Classis, yet undecided, therefore at this V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>stry it is conceived unfitting to proceed any further therein, but leave it to the Classis who are desired to determine the same; and that if the Classis should resolve of his admittance, and thereof signifie so much to us, wee shall bee willing to accept of him, and in the meane time wee desire him to forbeare.</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Untill this time there was no fit opportunity for the Messengers Master L. Colonell <hi>H.</hi> and Colonell <hi>B.</hi> (according to the Order of the <hi>Classis</hi>) to deliver their Message to Master <hi>Symonds,</hi> and the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture day drawing on, Master <hi>Bellamy</hi> came very late to Master <hi>Ley</hi> (the night after the Vestry had made their resolution forementi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned, <hi>viz. Jan.</hi> 10.) to consult about a visit of Master <hi>Symonds</hi> on the morrow being the next day before hee was expected to enter upon the expository Lecture. But that (upon consideration) was conceived unseasonable for it was very probable in their appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hensions
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:95407:6"/> that the matter was already resolved on betwixt Mr. <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds</hi> and his principall Auditors, and then if upon their comming his mind should have beene changed, and the people disappointed of the Lecture, it would bee imputed to them with as harsh a cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure as passed on the Order of the Classis before, but with louder <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>aour, since the provocation would bee more publique, more ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, and it may bee also by union (at their meeting together) more violent; and on the contrary, if hee should preach after they had been with him, it would haply bee said they had approved of him, (which they could not doe before they had imparted their message, and reported his answer to the <hi>Classis,</hi> and heard their judgement upon it) or that hee and his party had contemned the Classis; and therefore it was thought best to leave him to the reso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of his owne counsell and choyce; which though it were with some doubting for a time, was setled at last for his preaching a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his owne Letter to Mr. <hi>Ley</hi> sheweth in these words.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>To his Reverend friend Mr. <hi>Ley</hi> Minister at St. <hi>Mary Hill.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sir, fearing misconstructions of an act of mine this day, and desiring to carry all things in love and peace, I held it meet to give you an accompt as to a Brother of the businesse; Sir, the Parish in Cornhill did desire mee to forbeare preaching till your Classis had determined, and I did fully in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend it, yea I did not so much as make the least preparation, being unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to take any way but that which might bee with most peace, though they that were deputed with you to speake with mee did declare that they were sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied, and that I might preach: I sent this morning to Colonell</hi> Bellamy <hi>to know if I might preach, and found I might not; upon this I held off all thoughts of preaching. About two of the Clook some told mee people ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered but the doores were kept shut, upon which I sent againe to Col.</hi> Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamy <hi>to know whether the doores should bee opened if I came, (which I did to keepe peace) his answer was bee could say nothing to it, or to that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose: afterwards one brought word the doores were opened, and the people sitting in expectation of mee; hereupon I went, having no time to recollect thoughts, and in the simplicitie of my heart, God knoweth, I tooke this as an unquestisnable evidence that the Parish had consented; and I was glad to goe, hoping it would prevent much unquietnesse in the Citie. But I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive now it is otherwise in that Parish. It is true when I was in the Church, and going to the pulpit, the Clarke did pray mee not to preach, and hee one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; but I did it, being earnestly pressed, fearing it would have savoured ill if the people had beene turned backe. Sir, I have dealt candidly with
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:95407:7"/> you, that you may both know and make knowne my action in the reason of it and my end; I beseech you take this in love from</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your Brother and servant in Christ, I. Symonds.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>This Letter was brought to Mr. <hi>L.</hi> upon Tuesday night, <hi>Jan.</hi> 12. by Mr. <hi>Po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>k</hi> his son, (at whose house hee then lodged;) by whom Mr. <hi>L.</hi> signified to Mr. <hi>Symonds</hi> that if hee would yet name the time and place, himselfe with the other two members of the <hi>Classis,</hi> Col. <hi>Hooker</hi> and Col. <hi>Bell<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>my</hi> would come to him; but hee made no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to Mr. <hi>Symonds</hi> in writing,</p>
            <p>First, because hee had no authoritie to treate with him alone in that businesse.</p>
            <p>Secondly, for that the state of the question seemed now to him to bee much changed from what it was, and so to bee fit for a new consulation of the Classis.</p>
            <p>Yet conceiving it to bee necessary to find a time to speake with him before the next Classicall Assembly, they consulted againe about it, and after mutuall premonition betwixt Mr. <hi>Symonds</hi> and them they resolved upon Friday morning, <hi>Jan.</hi> 15. at eight of the Clock to goe to him at his lodging, and accordingly they did so; where they told him that the Ministers and Elders of the Classis appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them to acquaint him with two particulars, the one was the Ordinance of Parliament touching ordination of Ministers, <hi>Aug.</hi> 28. 1646. wherein it is provided, <hi>that every person, formerly ordained a Presbyter according to the forme of ordination which haeth beene held in the Church of England, and is to bee removed to another charge, bring to the Presbytery where he is to bee placed, if there bee any; and if not, then to some other Presbytery a Testimoniall of his Ordination, and of his abilities and conversation, whereupon his fitnesse for that place to which hee is to bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved shall bee tryed by his preaching there, and (if it shall bee judged ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary) by a further examination.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The other particular was a report that hee was of opinion for toleration of different religions, not onely of <hi>Br<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>wnists, Anabaptists</hi> and <hi>Familists</hi> on the one hand, but of <hi>Papists</hi> on the other, and thereupon hee was desired to returne his resolution whether hee would enter upon the Lecture according to the Tenour of the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, and give the right hand of fellowship to his brethren of the <hi>Classis,</hi> and so manage his Ministry in that Lecture as might most conduce to the edification of the people, the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therance of the reformation set on foot, and the preservation of the peace of the Church and State; and that what answer so ever
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:95407:7"/> it pleased him to give to these particulars it is left to his libertie to give it by them who were sent from the <hi>Classis,</hi> or to bring it him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe, or to send it in writing to them at their next meeting.</p>
            <p>Hee replyed hee would give answer by them that brought the message, and then spake to three points.</p>
            <p>First, to the reason of his removall out of <hi>Holland</hi> into <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, to the report of his opinion for toleration of diversitle of Religions.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, to his resolution required touching conforming to the Ordinance.</p>
            <p>For the first, hee made a very sad and sensible declaration of the destitution of his bodily health, and indisposition of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties of his mind, (and sometimes also of his speech) for his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisteriall function in <hi>Holland,</hi> proceeding <hi>from</hi> the violence of the <hi>Flatus hypochondriacus</hi> (a melancholick windinesse of the spleene <hi>front</hi> the distemper of the <hi>diaphragma</hi> or Midriffe, and from the palpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the heart, and other symptomes of sicknesse inclining to an Apoplexy) which hee imputed principally to the ayre of <hi>Holland,</hi> and conceived that the ayre of his native Country would cure him of these diseases; and hee had (as hee said) experience to confirme him in that conceit, because upon the changes of ayre hee presently perceived very great changes in the constitution of his body for the better, (when hee came out of <hi>Holland</hi> into <hi>England</hi>) for the worse (when hee returned thence to <hi>Holland</hi> againe.)</p>
            <p>Secondly, for the report, hee said that hee never preached any such doctrine as hee was charged withall; It was answered the charge was not raised so high as the Pulpit, for it was said but that he spake it or wrote it to a friend in a Letter, yet if hee held such a Tenet (though yet his preaching of it could not bee proved) hee might haply preach it hereafter. Hee replyed that hee had preached the contrary this last yeere, and had condemned toleration of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versitie of Religions in foure cases, which were these, <hi>viz</hi> when it is</p>
            <list>
               <head>Repugnant</head>
               <item>1. To the Faith.</item>
               <item>2. To godlinesse of life.</item>
               <item>3. To humane societie. And</item>
               <item>4. To civill authoritie.</item>
            </list>
            <p>And for the Letter which <note n="*" place="margin">The Copy of a letter writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten from a god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Minister in <hi>Holland</hi> to some reverend and godly Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters here in <hi>London, Third part of the G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grena, p.</hi> 16<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> was published by Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> wherein the writer saith of Mr. <hi>Symonds, I heare that Mr. Symonds hath writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to his Congregation here very confidently that toleration shall be granted,</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:95407:8"/> even with these termes <hi>inspight of them who have enterprised the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</hi> Hee disavowed the allegation both for words and matter, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging no more but that in a Letter to a friend hee had inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated an hope of good compliance, and mutuall forbearance of brethren, (notwithstanding some differences in judgement and practice in points of lesse moment then those forementioned) and that hee would endeavour to preserve Christian concord both a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst Ministers and People in the exercise of his Ministery.</p>
            <p>And for the third, hee said hee tooke it, that his case was not within the compasse of the Ordinance, because hee was not to take upon him a pastorall charge, whereas the Ordinance speakes not of a <hi>pastor</hi> but of a Presbyter, and wee conceive Master <hi>Symonds</hi> to bee such an one, and though it mention a <hi>charge,</hi> yet doth it not specifie a <hi>pastorall charge,</hi> but leaveth the word <hi>charge</hi> in such a latitude as may take in undertakings of very distinct and different kinds, and so wee finde it in the scripture, as the charge of the sonnes of <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shon</hi> was the <hi>Tabernacle, and the Tent, and the covering thereof, and the hanging for the doore of the Tabernacle,</hi> Numb: 3. 25. <hi>The charge of the Cohathites was the Arke, and the Table, and the Candlesticke, and the Altars, and the vessels of the Sanctuary, and the hangings, and all the service thereof, v:</hi> 31. The charge of the <hi>Levites for killing the Passeover, 2 Chron: 30. 17. and the charge</hi> of the decree <hi>for destruction of the Jewes, Esth:</hi> 3. 9. These differ more then a Lecture doth from a parochiall incumbency, yet all of them are comprehended in the name of a <hi>charge;</hi> but if the Ordinance had expresly named a <hi>pasto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall charge,</hi> a <hi>parsonage or benefice,</hi> the intent and scope of the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance might, and in reasonable construction, should reach also to <hi>a Lecture,</hi> as hath beene formerly shewed in defence of the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice given to the Vestry of <hi>Michael Cornehill,</hi> in the Order of the <hi>Classis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object:</hi> But though the Ordinance reach to a Lecturer obliging him with others to give an accompt, it reacheth not unto a <hi>Classis,</hi> say some, to authorise them to take the accompt either of a Lectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer or Beneficed pastor, but to the Presbytery where they are to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiate.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Answ:</hi> First, if there bee no Presbytery there, then the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance saith the testimoniall may bee tendred to, and the tryall made by some other Presbytery, and that Presbytery may bee <hi>Classicall,</hi> as well as <hi>Congregationall;</hi> and rather Classicall, because Classicall Presbyteries have power to constitute Presbyteries Congregatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:95407:8"/> and in defect of them, Parishes are to bee immediately under the Classis within whose circuit they are fitnate, according to the directions of the Lords and Commons <hi>Die Martis 19 Augusti</hi> 1645. for the election of Elders, <hi>p.</hi> 8. 9. and such was the condition of <hi>Michaels Cornhill</hi> at that time when they made their first motion of the matter unto the <hi>Classis</hi> concerning Master <hi>Symonds.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, If their Presbytery had beene perfect in the consti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutive Members thereof, they might in a case of doubtfull debate, (as that was about the preaching place for the new Lecturer) de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire the advice of the Classis, and the Classis might as well returne their advice as they require it at their hands upon the ground and evidence formerly alleadged. Howsoever <hi>Master</hi> Symonds <hi>promised that if he tooke upon him a pastorall charge of a particular Congregation, he would make his entrance into it by the way of the Ordinance. In the meane time if in his Lecture he said any thing contrary to faith or godliness, or tend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to a disturbance of humane society, or the Civill state, he would be ready to give an accompt thereof to the Classicall Assembly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And hee concluded with a complaint that hee was not well dealt withall, neither by the Vestry of <hi>Michaels Cornhill,</hi> (because as hee said, hee should have beene advertised by them of the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception against him in private before they presented it to the Clas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sis in publique) Nor by the Classis, because they should have done the like before they had ordered any thing against his admission, especially since being <hi>a Presbyter, an accusation should not have beene re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived but under two or three witnesses.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereto for the Vestry of <hi>Michaels Cornhill,</hi> Master <hi>Bellamy</hi> one of that society said that hee must cleare the Vestry from that charge, and if there were any fault in acquainting the Classis with it hee must take it to himselfe so farre as to confesse hee was the first mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver thereof, but he hoped for that hee had not done amisse, as hee was assured hee had no meaning therein to doe any thing to the prejudice either of the Lecture or Lecturer there, and for what hee did hee had this inducement; (which he conceived both weighty in reason and warrantable in conscience) In the debate of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, hee observed the sway of affections (besides the difference of judgements) to grow to some heate, which did not tend to a settle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment on such a conclusion as might bee like to preserve the peace of the parish; therefore hee propounded, and thereto both parties assented, to make an addresse to the Classis about it, and to desire from them advice for the determination of that difference which
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:95407:9"/> could not bee so well composed among themselves. Thus for the objection to the Vestry in <hi>Cornhill.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And for the <hi>Classis</hi> Master <hi>Ley</hi> (if the time had permitted) would have put in an Apology; but he was in <hi>haste,</hi> (having staid beyond his houre for his necessary attendance at the Assembly,) and in <hi>hope</hi> of another opportunity, which would bee most seasonable, when the objection had beene proposed to the <hi>Classis,</hi> as since it hath beene, and their answer to it is, That the accusation was not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived in the sence of the Apostle, 1 <hi>Tim:</hi> 5. 19. that is, not so farre beleived, as upon it to proceed to any judiciall examination of the proofe, or censure of the party against whom it was made; but was rather suspended for the clearing of Master <hi>Symonds</hi> if hee were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent, then admitted as a convincing evidence against him. And if the witnesse were but one, as hee said, there was such weight in that one as might well put both the Vestry and Classis to a pause touching his approbation, though not to a repulse of him in their finall resolution.</p>
            <p>But yet there was more then a single testimony in the charge, when besides the saying of that knowne witnesse there was a letter alleadged in the Classis sounding to the like sence, the proofe where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, was afterwards offered to some of the Classis by a Reverend Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister. Neverthelesse the Classis gave so much credit to Master <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds</hi> his answer, as to conceive that whatsoever his opinion was in former times hee was now Orthodox, in judgement against such a toleration as was objected unto him; and therefore upon due consideration of what was reported to them by their Messengers, <hi>Jan:</hi> 10. they resolved, <hi>That notwithstanding some informations from very good hands concerning Master</hi> Symonds <hi>opinion for toleration of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versity of Religions, (Popery not excepted) having now received by way of answer from his owne mouth (made to such as were sent from the Classis to conferre with him about it) that he disavoxeth that opinion, and averreth that hee hath preached the contrary doctrine this last summer, when the same shall bee testified under his hand to the Classis, they are willing and doe give advice to the Parish of</hi> Michaels Cornhill <hi>to admit him to preach the expository Lecture in the said Church, as Master</hi> Burroughs <hi>lately did.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If they had further advised that the Vestry of <hi>Michaels Cornbill</hi> should not accept of him for a Lecturer in their Church untill hee had disclaimed Independency, or engaged his promise against ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering of Churches, they had acted but according to the temper
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:95407:9"/> of their zeale, who are not pleased with the proceedings of the Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stry and Classis in Master <hi>Symonds</hi> his cause; And if their zeale for Presbytery had gone a quicker pace then theire for Independency, it had been much more warrantable in them, since Presbytery (with the graduall subordinations, Congregationall, Classicall, Provincial, and Nationall,) is set up by the supreme Judicatory of the kingdom, and thereby is Independency at least virtually put downe.</p>
            <p>But because <hi>first,</hi> Master <hi>Symonds</hi> was not for the present resident within the limits of the fourth Classis, nor <hi>secondly,</hi> limited for the Lecture either to that or any other particular Church; <hi>thirdly,</hi> for that he was represented unto many of the brethren (by such as well knew him) as a man of a quiet and peaceable spirit, and was so apprehended and reported of by those who by the <hi>Classis</hi> were sent to him, and had conference with him; and <hi>lastly</hi> because hee inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated a motion made to him for taking of a pastorall charge, and shewed no aversnesse from acceptation thereof, the <hi>Classis</hi> thought fit to propound none other condition at that time in their advice to the Vestry of <hi>Michaels Cornhill</hi> then the setting done of that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his hand, which hee had said with his tongue, as a double te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stimony of the integrity of his heart, which they conceived would conduce as much to his own clearing from that impious opinion of toleration of erroneous and hereticall Religions, as for satisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of any who did or might take offence at him for such a Tenet.</p>
            <p>Upon such reasons as these it was resolved by the Classis not only that their second advice to the Parish of <hi>Michaels Cornhil</hi> should bee drawne up into an Order, and sent unto them, but a Copy of it also bee transmitted by some of them to the subscribers for that Lecture, at their meeting appointed at Master <hi>Shutes</hi> the Wednesday following at 8 of the Clocke in the morning, where, after some de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate of the matter betwixt Master <hi>Symonds</hi> and themselves, they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded negatively <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>against his writing and subscribing as it was propounded by the Classis, and that if by Saturday following the Parishioners of <hi>Michaels Cornhill</hi> would not yeild to admit him to preach in their Church, (which was contrary to the expresse ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of the Classis sent unto them, and to their owne Resolution upon it, made knowne to Master <hi>Symonds</hi>) that then the Lecture should bee renewed, removed, and settled at <hi>Ab-Church.</hi> Yet some who were well pleased with the choyce of Master <hi>Symonds</hi> dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liked the change of the Church, and therefore (when they saw no
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:95407:10"/> hope of the subscribers yeelding to Mr. <hi>Symonds</hi> his giving satisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the <hi>Classis,</hi> and Parish in that particular (and without their consent to have done it might have proved to his losse) some of them dealt with some of the <hi>Classis</hi> to procure another meeting of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters and Elders in a Classicall Assembly before the Sabbath day following, where it should bee propounded to the Classis to reverse their late advice to the Parish of <hi>Michaels Cornhill,</hi> and to rest con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented with Mr. <hi>Symonds</hi> his clearing, as it was represented to them by their owne Messengers.</p>
            <p>Which was a thing as difficult to bee brought about in so short a time, as unreasonable to bee desired; for why should they bee mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to meet twice in one weeke, who are appointed by the directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Parliament to meet but once a moneth, though they be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by the same Authoritie to assemble more often if they see cause? and why should they bee called together againe so soone to recall that which (upon so just considerations and reasons) was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed on by them, and without the like inducements was denied by Mr. <hi>Symonds</hi> and the subscribers to the Lecture? how much more easie and equall had it beene for him and them to have assented to the Classis in that they desired, then for the Classis without any further correspondence on their part, to renounce their owne deliberate, and (as they yet conceive) well grounded advice, and to lay themselves open thereby to the imputation of levitie, for undo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it; and it may bee also of injury, for what they had done in their precedent proceedings.</p>
            <p>It was not then without cause that the Vestry of <hi>Michaels Cornhill</hi> in conformitie to the Classis did at their meeting, <hi>Jan.</hi> 21. (not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding the finall refusall of Mr. <hi>Symonds</hi> and the subscribers to admit of the condition of his admission the day before) set down their resolution for this matter by a writing of this tenour. <hi>Whereas the Parish of Michaels Cornhill have received an Order from the Classis, touching an acknowledgement to hee made under the hand of Mr. Symonds and the admission of him to preach the exposition Lecture there, it was this day ordered at a Vestry holden in the said Parish, that Mr. William Rowell and Col. Bellamy shall goe to Mr. Symonds, and signifie to him from the Parish, if hee will subscribe the said acknowledgmet in accomplish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the said Order of the Classis, that then the Parishioners are willing and desirous that the said exposition Lecture shall bee by him preached in the said Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The messengers according to the Order went to Mr. <hi>Sym.</hi> his lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:95407:10"/> but be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>use hee was not then within, they left the Order for him with his wife. In this order it was resolved onely on the <hi>posi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive</hi> part according to that they received from the Classis, leaving the <hi>negative</hi> to bee made up by Mr. <hi>Symonds,</hi> and them whose coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sels are of more value with him then his Presbyteriall Brethrens. Yet however they bee slighted, or censured by them, their purpose is without all uncharitable returnes to any of them, (as holding it an happier thing to suffer then to offer or answer a contumely in the same kind) to passe through good report and bad report in the conscionable discharge of that dutie whereto God hath called them, and for which the authoritie of Parliament hath enabled them.</p>
            <p>And for such of our brethren as thinke the Classis might and ought to have done more by vertue of the Ordinance, alledging to that purpose the instance in the case of Mr. <hi>Sp.</hi> forementioned, they shall doe well to consider that the case of Mr. <hi>Symonds</hi> and his par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie is much unlike that of Mr. <hi>Sp.</hi> and the Company of Mercers; for (to say nothing of the disparitie of the two Divines, whereof the one hath beene accused upon divers Articles exhibited against him to a Committee of Parliament, as the other hath not.)</p>
            <p>First, there is a difference of importance betwixt the Patrons of each Lecture. For those who have had most sway in setting up and upholding these expository Lectures are professed Independents, and as such will not submit to any Classicall resolution; The Company of Mercers (for the most part and best sort of them) are for ought wee know regular men, who agree to the Government set up by Ordinance of Parliament, and as such would take a repulse or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall from a Classis with more patience, then the other will a pause or demurrein that they desire.</p>
            <p>Secondly, that Lecture to which Mr. <hi>Sp.</hi> was nominated might receive a finall determination from that Classis which required his forbearance to preach, because it is confined to <hi>Bartholomews</hi> Church, it being a monethly Lecture set up for Sacramentall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration there onely, this of Mr. <hi>Symonds</hi> not so to <hi>Michael Cornhill</hi> but that it may bee as well removed to any other Church, or Classis, of the Province, as renewed there; and therefore the finall ordering thereof doth more properly belong to the Provinciall then to any Classicall Assembly.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, there was no need for the fourth Classis to doe more then what they did, since what they have already done (yea their
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:95407:11"/> first advice alone, received with the left hand though tendered with the right) was enough to provoke, and more would have been too little to prevaile with men so resolved to stand out, as the subscri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers partly appeared before, but now the event hath more fully dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered; And we hope also by this apologeticall report of the truth, equitablenesse, and moderation of our proceedings with Mr. <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds</hi> will bee so farre cleared to all Religious and impartiall Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, as that it will not onely confute the falshood of such reports as have passed upon them, but prevent the like, at least the beliefe of them, with the better and wiser sort in time to come.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:95407:11"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>